Guide to the International Center for Transitional Justice (ICTJ) records, 1918-2020, bulk 1970-2020 RL.01304
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
International Center for Transitional Justice (ICTJ) records
1918-2020
1970-2020
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
International Center for Transitional Justice
RL.01304
221 Linear Feet 155 boxes; 3 oversize folders
2700 Gigabytes
The International Center for Transitional Justice (ICTJ) is a non-profit organization that assists countries in pursuing accountability for mass atrocities and human rights abuses. Its records span the years 1918 to 2020, with the bulk of the materials dating from the 1970s-2020. Materials include ICTJ office and administrative files, program and conference records, annual reports, legal journals, human rights organization publications, reports and white papers, newspapers, subject files, teaching materials, trial transcripts, and posters and ephemera. There are many audiovisual and digital records. Groups and governing bodies represented in the materials include ICTJ, Amnesty International, United Nations organizations and missions, the European Union, the Washington Office on Latin America, the World Bank, Minority Rights Group International, criminal courts, truth commissions, and many others. Administrative files include the papers of former ICTJ Presidents and other staff files, including Juan E. Mendez, Priscilla Hayner, Louis Bickford, Alex Boraine, Ian Martin, Lisa Magarrell, and Marieke Wierda -- as well as institutional memory files that document the narrative of the creation and work of ICTJ. Acquired as part of the Human Rights Archive at Duke University.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged into five series: Geographic Files; Reference and Reports; Program and Subject Files; Administrative Records; and Audiovisual Materials.
Biographical / Historical
The International Center for Transitional Justice (ICTJ), founded in 2001 and based in New York City, is a global non-profit that works with partners in post-conflict, conflict, and democratic countries to pursue accountability, truth, and reconciliation for large-scale human right abuses, through a series of measures including criminal prosecutions, truth commissions, reparations programs, and institutional reforms. It also has offices in Bogotá, Colombia; Brussels, Belgium; The Hague, The Netherlands; Kampala, Uganda; Nairobi, Kenya; and Tunis, Tunisia.
Access Restrictions
Access note. Collection contains fragile audiovisual/photographic formats that may need to be reformatted before use. Contact the Rubenstein Library for access.
Access note. Collection contains electronic records that must be requested and accessed in our reading room. Contact the Rubenstein Library for access to these files.
Provenance
The International Center for Transitional Justice Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift between 2008 and 2021.
Collection Overview
The records of the International Center for Transitional Justice (ICTJ) span the years 1918 to 2020, with the bulk of the materials from the late 20th and early 21st century. The materials document the activities of ICTJ in its support of peace processes and to the pursuit of legal reparations and reconciliation in areas of conflict involving human rights violations. Formats in the collection include ICTF office and administrative files, annual reports, single articles, legal journals, human rights organization publications, reports and white papers, conference proceedings, newspapers and clippings, trial transcripts, teaching materials, and photographs, as well as some posters and other ephemera such as fliers, graphics, invitations, and programs. There are many audiovisual and digital formats.
There are four main series: Geographic Files, Reference and Reports, Program and Subject Files, and Administrative Files. The Geographic series contains materials from countries directly impacted by the work of ICTJ and its partners. It is arranged by continent and then by country. These materials cover virtually every major case of human rights abuse and violation worldwide. There are also materials on affiliated armed conflicts such as the Iraq War and the war in Bosnia-Herzegovina; violent ethnic clashes; refugee movements; refugee and detention camps; women's rights; and case studies of human rights abuses.
The Reference and Reports series formed ICTJ's documentation library. The Program and Subject files contain thematically-arranged publications about ICTJ's main subject areas, such as transitional justice and reparations, as well as the programatic materials from ICTJ conferences, workshops, publications, truth commissions, and program divisions. The final series, administrative files, is largely comprised of the files of former ICTJ presidents Alex Boraine and Juan Mendez and other staff files, including Louis Bickford, director of multiple ICTJ units. The staff files and the institutional memory files come together to form the narrative of the creation and work of ICTJ since its beginnings in 2001.
Each series also lists audiovisual materials and digital files. These materials are inserted into the series they correspond with. Formats include Betamax tapes, mini-DVs, DVDs, CDs, VHS tapes, and cassette tapes. The audiovisual materials include trial recordings, staff interviews, conference recordings, and truth commission proceedings; some of these were digitized by ICTJ staff. The born-digital records contain similar materials and also include training materials, ICTJ administrative materials, and program specific documents.
Acquired as part of the Human Rights Archive at Duke University.
African Americans -- North Carolina -- Greensboro; AIDS (Disease) -- Organizations; Apartheid -- South Africa; Children (International law); Developing countries -- Social conditions; Developing countries -- Economic conditions; Dictatorship -- Latin America -- History -- 20th century; Genocide; Human Rights -- Periodicals; Human rights advocacy; Human rights monitoring; Human rights workers; Humanitarian assistance; Indians, Treatment of -- North America; Internally displaced persons; International courts -- History -- 20th century; International law -- Cases; Non-governmental organizations; Peace-building; Reconciliation; Transitional justice; Truth commissions -- History; Women's rights -- International cooperation; Africa -- Ethnic relations; Africa -- Foreign relations; Africa -- Politics and government -- 1960-; Asia -- Politics and government -- 1945-; Caribbean Area -- Politics and government -- 1945-; Caribbean Area -- Social conditions -- 1945-; Central America -- Foreign relations -- United States; Central America -- Politics and government -- 1979-; Central America -- Social conditions; Greensboro (N.C.) -- Race relations; Latin America -- Foreign relations -- United States; Latin America -- Politics and government -- 20th century; Latin America -- Social conditions; Audiocassettes; Mini-DV; Optical disks; Photographs; Videocassettes; International Center for Transitional Justice; Human Rights Archive (Duke University); Méndez, Juan E.; Hayner, Priscilla B.; Wierda, Marieke; Boraine, Alex; Bickford, Louis; Darko, Eric; Gutierrez, Blaz; Magarrell, Lisa; Nesiah, Vasuki; Martin, Ian, 1946-; Amnesty International; Atlantic Philanthropists; Center for Democratic Development (Ghana); Human Rights Watch; International Criminal Court; International Crisis Group; Carnegie Council on Ethics & International Affairs; Ford Foundation; Greensboro Truth & Reconciliation Commission; International Center for Human Rights and Democratic Development; Ku Klux Klan (1915- ) -- North Carolina; Latin American Network on Transitional Justice; Lawyers Committee for Human Rights; Minority Rights Group International; Office of the UN High Commissioner for Human Rights; Open Society Justice Initiative; Unesco; UNICEF; United Nations. General Assembly; United Nations. Department of Peace-keeping Operations; United Nations Development Programme; United States Institute of Peace; Washington Office on Latin America; World Bank
- Geographic Files, 1918-2016; 1969-2016
  Scope and Contents
  The Geographic series, the largest in the collection, is comprised of files representing about 100 countries and forms the backbone of ICTJ's collection. The country files include ICTJ reports, journal articles, publications about governance, rule of law, political stability, reparations, and human rights violations, as well as materials from various country's truth and reconciliation commissions. These materials are unique to each country and provide insight into the impact ICTJ's work has on every citizen, from victims to perpetrators, children and women to ex-combatants.
  Arrangement
  Divided into subseries, by continent, for Africa, Asia, Europe, North America/Caribbean, and South/Central America. Organized within continental subseries with a multi-regional section first, followed by country files in alphabetical order.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Contact Research Services in advance to request the production of viewing/listening copies.
  - Multi-Continent, 1984-2005
    The multi-continent records contain oversize posters and newspapers collected by ICTJ from several countries across the globe.
    - Multi-regional, 1984-2005; 13 folders (Oversize-box 120-122, Folder Oversize Folder 1)
      Oversize material including newspapers from Afghanistan, Sierra Leone, Zimbabwe, and Ghana and posters from Colombia, East Timor, Germany, Liberia, Kenya, and Latin America.
  - Africa, 1969-2015
    Each African country contains journal articles and other publications, including ICTJ reports, related to governance, rule of law, political stability, truth and reconciliation, reparations, and human rights violations. Materials are chiefly in English, but these records do contain some materials in French.
    Electronic records in this sub-series have been migrated to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access, please contact Research Services before coming to use these records.
    - Multi-regional, 1995-2014; 4 folders (Box 1)
      Contains articles on multiple African countries.
    - Multi-regional Audiovisual Materials
      Includes public hearings, NGO video, and UN directory of African NGOs.
      - Buying Time for Peace, 2006; DVD (Box 132, Dvd RL01304-DVD-0033)
      - Community Service in Africa: An Alternative to Imprisonment, 2002; VHS (Box 125, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0090)
        Penal Reform International production
      - ECOMOG in Action, VHS (Box 125, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0065)
        Economic Community of West African States Monitoring Group
      - Public Hearing South Africa and Nigeria, VHS (Box 126, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0127)
      - Public Hearings South Africa and Nigeria, VHS (Box 127, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0166)
      - UN Directory of African NGOs, CD (Box 137, Cd RL01304-CD-0173)
    - Algeria, 2002-2003; 1 folders (Box 1)
      Human Rights Commission memorandum on the disappeared; NGO statements on the new commission
    - Algeria, 2006; 1 folders (Box 1)
      ICTJ Justice and Peace Project
    - Angola, 2006-2007; 2 folders (Box 1)
      A conflict summary and correspondence between ICTJ and the Angolan government about assistance with peacebuilding.
    - Burundi, 2002-2009; 5 folders (Box 1)
      ICTJ trip reports, a framework for ICTJ work in Burundi, articles about peace agreements, UN Security Council Resolution 1545, ICTJ correspondence to Burundi officials, and an International Crisis Group report on elections.
    - Chad, 1993-2006; 3 folders (Box 1)
      National report on crimes (French), the Tripoli Agreement, and a conflict summary.
    - Congo/Democratic Republic of Congo, 2002-2012; 11 folders (Box 1)
      International Crisis Group report on Ituri problem and briefing, a conflict summary, peace agreements between Congo, Rwanda, Tanzania, and Uganda, UN Security Council Resolutions, ICTJ trip reports, DRC needs assessment by ICTJ, "Living with Fear" article, and UN reports, ICJP reports (French).
    - Congo/Democratic Republic of Congo, 2011; 5 folders (Box 1)
      Draft report of human rights violations in the Democratic Republic of Congo.
    - Cote d' Ivoire, 2003-2013; 6 folders (Box 1)
      UN Security Council Resolutions, ICTJ Criminal Justice Assessment report, ICTJ trip reports, ICTJ mission reports, International Criminal Court reports, ICTJ assessment protocol, UN General Assembly reports, ICTJ country plan, Cote d'Ivoire penal code and military code (French), CDVR and ICTJ country meeting, International Crisis Group report on peacebuilding.
    - Ethiopia and Eritrea, 1995-2003; 4 folders (Box 2)
      Amnesty International report on human rights in transition, chronology of the reform movement in Eritrea, the Special Court and its role in the Eritrean judicial system, news articles, subject articles, UN Security Council reports, UN General Assembly reports, UN Mission in Eritrea and Ethiopia fact sheet.
    - Ethiopia, 1995-1999; 2 folders (Box 2)
      African Studies Association of the UK Conference panel "Ethiopia: The Dergue Trials", Amnesty International reports on human rights and the Dergue trials.
    - Gabon, 2001 July 26; 1 folders (Box 2)
      Memo from Ludovic Hood to ICTJ about President Omar Albert-Bernard Bongo's regime.
    - Gambia, 2002-2004; 1 folders (Box 2)
      Correspondence from Gambian government informing ICTJ of receipt of annual reports.
    - Ghana, 2000-2008; 10 folders (Box 2)
      Center for Democratic Development (CDD) briefing papers, ICTJ and CDD correspondence, National Reconciliation Commission (NRC) bill, Constitution of Ghana, orders for parliamentary meetings, report of the NRC, NRC informational booklet, international conference on national reconciliation, news articles, correspondence between ICTJ and Ghanan government about reconciliation efforts, ICTJ trip reports, notes about ICTJ involvement in NRC, list of University of Ghana Law faculty alumni, statements by the Ghana attorney general.
    - Ghana Audiovisual Materials
      - Bishop Buckle and Prof. M. Bonsu, Mini-DV (Box 139, Video-cassette RL01304-MDV-0011)
      - Ghana/General Erskine, Mini-DV (Box 139, Video-cassette RL01304-MDV-0006)
      - Ghana/MW Adams, Gen. Erskine, Mini-DV (Box 139, Video-cassette RL01304-MDV-0008)
    - Guinea, 2007-2008; 1 folders (Box 2)
      Request from ICTJ to the Consulate of Guinea for a travel visa.
    - Kenya, 1998-2009; 14 folders (Box 2-3)
      Kenya National Committee on Human Rights (KNCHR) progress report on post-election violence, preliminary report on executions and disappearances, KNCHR report on investigations of torture at Mt. Elgon, ICTJ trip reports, Kenya National Dialogue and Reconciliation reports and statements, police reforms, Human Rights Watch articles, feedback forms from a workshop on Kenyan validation, ICTJ Kenya programming, draft bill of the Constitution of Kenya, submissions of the Constitution of Kenya Review Commission to the National Constitutional Conference, proposed adjustments to the Truth and Reconciliation bill, Kenya We Want conference.
    - Liberia, 1993-2008; 15 folders (Box 3)
      Observations on transitional justice in Liberia, ICTJ implementation plans, ICTJ proposal for Truth and Reconciliation Commission in Liberia, ICTJ trip reports, reparations timeline, act to create the Independent National Commission on Human Rights of Liberia, peacebuilding commission creation and implementation, ICTJ mission reports, UN Security Council Resolutions, recommendations to the UN Security Council, International Crisis Group articles and Africa briefing, International Conference for the Reconstruction of Liberia, Constitution of Liberia, ICTJ proposed plan of action, Amnesty International article, Global Rights report on prospects and challenges for human rights protection in Liberia, NGO updates, UN statement on Liberia.
    - Liberia Audiovisual Materials
      Series of 9 interviews, at the ICTJ office in New York, with three women from Liberia.
      - Interviews with the 3 women from Liberia at ICTJ office, 2008-07-23; Mini-DV (Box 139, Video-cassette RL01304-MDV-0095)
      - Liberia Interviews Tape 1, 2008-01-29/2008-01-30; Mini-DV (Box 139, Video-cassette RL01304-MDV-0096)
      - Liberia Interviews Tape 2, 2008-01-30; Mini-DV (Box 139, Video-cassette RL01304-MDV-0097)
      - Liberia Interviews Tape 3, 2008-01-30/2008-01-31; Mini-DV (Box 139, Video-cassette RL01304-MDV-0098)
      - Liberia Interviews Tape 4, 2008-01-31; Mini-DV (Box 139, Video-cassette RL01304-MDV-0099)
      - Liberia Interviews Tape 5, 2008-02-01; Mini-DV (Box 139, Video-cassette RL01304-MDV-0100)
      - Liberia Interviews Tape 6, 2008-02-02; Mini-DV (Box 139, Video-cassette RL01304-MDV-0101)
      - Liberia Interviews Tape 7, 2008-02-03; Mini-DV (Box 139, Video-cassette RL01304-MDV-0102)
      - Liberia Interviews Tape 8, 2008-02-03; Mini-DV (Box 139, Video-cassette RL01304-MDV-0103)
    - Mali, 2014 May; 1 folders (Box 3)
      Transitional Justice, Justice Reform, and Anti-Corruption Workshop organized by the government of Mali, the government of Qatar, Republic of France, and the UN Development Programme.
    - Morocco, 2001-2009; 8 folders (Box 3)
      US Institute of Peace special report on Morocco Truth and Reconciliation Commission, Kingdom of Morocco Equity and Reconciliation Commission final report volume III, Rabat report, Morocco Human Rights Advisory Council recommendations, ICTJ progress report on transitional justice in Morocco, subject articles, Kingdom of Morocco Ministry of Justice guidebook. Includes materials in Arabic.
    - Morocco Audiovisual Materials
      - Morocco #2, Mini-DV (Box 139, Video-cassette RL01304-MDV-0022)
      - Morocco #2, Mini-DV (Box 139, Video-cassette RL01304-MDV-0030)
    - Nigeria, 1997-2003; 8 folders (Box 3)
      Independent oversight report, news reports, Nigeria Human Rights Violations Investigations Commission reports, rulings, and documents, Tribunals of Inquiry Act, Federal Republic of Nigeria Official Gazette, a handbook for the 1999 elections, newspaper clippings, CDD news and reports, ICTJ trip reports, synoptic overview of conclusions and recommendations of the Human Rights Violations Investigation Commission.
    - Nigeria Audiovisual Materials
      Materials all related to the Truth and Reconciliation Commission trials and testimonies.
      - Bamaiyi on Coup (cont'd), VHS (Box 128, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0168)
      - Brief Nigerian Compilation, VHS (Box 127, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0136)
      - Diya's Cross Examination, 1999; VHS (Box 127, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0134)
      - Dr. Falamo, VHS (Box 127, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0167)
      - Gen Diya's Wives Petition, VHS (Box 126, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0128)
      - General Victor Malu Interrogation: Oputa Panel, 1999; VHS (Box 127, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0140)
      - Human Rights Violations Investigation Commission-Public Hearing of Commission: Lagos, 2000-11-13/2000-12-08; VHS (Box 127, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0162)
      - Human Rights Violations Investigation Commission-Public Hearing of Commission: Lagos, 2000-11-13/2000-12-08; VHS (Box 127, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0163)
      - Mathew Kukah, Mini-DV (Box 139, Video-cassette RL01304-MDV-0021)
      - Nigeria HRUC Hearings (duplicate?), VHS (Box 127, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0165)
      - Nigeria Oputa, 2000; Mini-DV (Box 139, Video-cassette RL01304-MDV-0055)
      - Nigeria Oputa, Mini-DV (Box 139, Video-cassette RL01304-MDV-0061)
      - Nigeria Oputa, Mini-DV (Box 139, Video-cassette RL01304-MDV-0063)
      - Oputa Commission Hearings, 1999; VHS (Box 127, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0137)
      - Oputa Commission Hearings, 1999; VHS (Box 127, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0138)
      - Oputa Commission Hearings, 1999; VHS (Box 127, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0142)
      - President of MOSOP's Testimony, 1999; VHS (Box 127, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0133)
      - Show #104, 2003-01-16; VHS (Box 127, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0132)
        PBS Frontline World show
      - Truth Commission Hearings, 1999; VHS (Box 127, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0139)
    - Rwanda, 1996-2007; 20 folders (Box 3-4)
      "Transition and Reconstruction of Rwanda's Socio-Economic Weave" article, Gacaca genocide articles and recommendations, discussions of punishment of those who participated in genocide, establishment of the Gacaca legislation, UN reports, subject articles about Rwandan Gacaca, Gacaca jurisdiction laws, Official Gazette of the Republic of Rwanda, Penal Reform International (PRI) reports on Gacaca jurisdictions and preparations, news articles, Rapport report, UN International Tribunal for Rwanda project for assistance to victims, International Criminal Tribunal report, ICG report.
    - Rwanda Audiovisual Materials
      - Akayesu-Audio Recording of motion to amend indictment, 1997-06-17; CD (Box 136, Cd RL01304-CD-0006)
      - Extract of Ruggiu trial, 2000-05-15; DVCAM (Box 131, Video-cassette RL01304-DVCAM-0016)
        International Criminal Tribunal for Rwanda
      - Judgement Bagilishema; Appeal Jdgt Akayesu, DVCAM (Box 131, Video-cassette RL01304-DVCAM-0015)
      - Justice and Rwanda Interviews, VHS (Box 125, Video-cassette RL01304-VHS-0064)
      - Towards Reconciliation; For the Victims; Justice Today, DVCAM (Box 131, Video-cassette RL01304-DVCAM-0014)
    - Sierra Leone, 1969; 1999-2009; 39 folders (Box 5-6)
      Study by PRIDE on ex-combatant views of the TRC, The Sierra Leone Working Group on Truth and Reconciliation report, ICTJ mission reports, ICTJ recommendations, ICTJ trip reports, ICTJ report "The Legacy of the TRC in Sierra Leone", UN Development Programme (UNDP) project to support reconciliation, UN peacekeeping, peace agreements between the government of Sierra Leone and the Revolutionary United Front, human rights cases and child perpetrators article, UNICEF involvement of children in TRC, impact of armed conflict on children report, evaluations of the TRC, National Forum for Human Rights annual report, UNAMSIL report on war related sexual violence, Sierra Leone Ministry of Finance report of the public expenditure tracking survey (PETS), Workmen's Compensation Act of 1969, HIV/AIDS crisis response from the Health Sector, CDC prevalence and behavioral risk factor survey, CDC comprehensive assessment of the HIV/AIDS crisis in Sierra Leone, Witness to Truth report, US Institute of Peace special report, Human Rights Watch briefing paper, news articles, UN press releases, UN Security Council Resolutions, White Paper Report of the TRC, Sierra Leone Bar Association publication, UN appeal to donors, UNAMSIL weekly HRC reports (2003), report from the Freetown Conference on Accountability in Sierra Leone, Special Court indictments, Special Court correspondence with ICTJ, Special Court best practices for protection and support of witnesses, statement takers manuel, Sierra Leone Rule of Law and Justice Sector capacity building project, ICTJ seminar on transitional justice, overview of gender justice, IPU seminar on reconciliation and institutional reform and the role of Parliament.
    - Sierra Leone, 2000-2005; 9 folders (Box 4-5)